Hello everyone. Welcome to Woood episode
10. My name is Rick.
>> My name is Susie.
>> And we're going to mark our 10 episode
milestone by talking all about
generations in the UK. So that's the
differences between people of different
generations. Starting with our
grandparents who are called the silent
generation to our parents who are called
boomers all the way through to people a
bit older than us who are Gen X our
generation the millennials then through
to Gen Z who are a bit younger than us
and then Gen Alpha who are still I think
they're still little kids aren't they?
>> Yeah up until age 15 I think.
>> Yes. And then finally the newest
generation which started this year. Gen
beta which is our children's generation
which is very scary and exciting.
>> You miss one off. We are missing the
greatest generation who are currently
about age 98 to 124.
>> Okay. So, yes, there still are some
people who are in their very late 90s
who are even older than our grandparents
generation. Um, we will get to them very
briefly, but um first uh yeah, Suz, what
you been up to?
>> Oh god, what have I been up to?
Something. Think of something
interesting.
>> Yeah, you're not very active these days.
I'm way more active than you.
>> Oh yeah. Yeah, of course. I forgot I'm
pregnant. So yeah, I've just been uh a
lot of waddling, eating, sitting, um
less exercise. Yeah, it's a bit sort of
um slow.
>> I can imagine. Yeah, but I think that's
your excuse every time like you don't
want to do something or if you feel like
you're not doing enough stuff, you can
just say, "Well, I'm pregnant, so I
don't have to do anything."
>> Yeah. So good. Yeah. Because you can
just You've always got a reason to say
no to things. It's like, "Oh, I I'm just
tired. I'm going to go cuz you know the
the twins are sleepy."
>> Yeah, that's good. And also you'll have
this excuse basically for the next 10
years of their lives cuz you can just
make up you can make up a problem or oh
I've got to take one of the twins to
this thing or they're sick or whatever.
Like you just make anything up so it's
easy.
>> It's definitely like a nesting thing as
well though cuz it's like I do want to
see people that I like but I don't want
to go anywhere. So I'm like come here
come to my house absolutely fine but I
am not venturing out into town. No.
>> Yeah. I think this is a very common
thing with new parents. They just want
to stay at home and sort of
domesticating yourself basically.
>> What about you?
>> Yeah, I was going to say I'm I'm doing
loads of stuff. I'm like really active
now and you're very inactive. So, we've
essentially swapped roles cuz when we
started doing this, I was very inactive
and you were like doing loads of stuff.
So, now we've swapped around which is
very interesting.
>> Oh. So, what have you been doing?
>> I'm in the process of moving to
Manchester, which is another city in the
UK that listeners may have heard of.
It's a very cool city up in the north.
And I'm going to move there in 2 weeks
time. So, I've got my new apartment,
which is very nice.
>> Quick. M I've sorted it out very
quickly.
>> Wow. You literally just went yesterday
or something, didn't you? To view flats.
>> Just the last weekend. Yeah. So, I did
it in a weekend and I'm going to move
down in the new year and I'm very
excited. It's a cool place. I think
Yeah. For our listeners, if you ever get
the chance, go to Manchester. It's an
interesting place. Uh there's lots to do
and it's a taste of the north of
England. I think a lot of people just go
to London and that's it. Definitely go
and see the North. It's worth seeing as
I'm sure you'd agree.
>> Yeah, there's a lot going on in
Manchester. What sort of flat have you
got? It's one of these new ones in a
former industrial area that they've
renovated and to be honest gentrified as
well, but it's a very nice apartment.
Yeah, I can't wait. It's just got it's
in a lovely complex as like an outdoor
area just for residents. Quite close to
the center. It's awesome. I can walk to
work again, which I couldn't do in Dubai
obviously because everybody has to
drive. So, I'm going to be more active
and yeah, I just can't wait.
>> M exciting for our next series. Then
we'll have to update on how is Rick's
life in Manchester and how is Suz's life
with twins the new updates whenever we
get round to the new series
>> of season 2. Yes. So let's start with uh
generations. I thought it was an
interesting one to do because there are
big different obviously we all have the
same generations all around the world
but there are some particular
differences in how generations work in
the UK and the west compared to
generations in other countries. So I
thought it was like really worth talking
about. But let's start with the oldest
generation and we'll work our way down
through all the different generations.
>> I thought it's quite a nice one because
it kind of ties together some things
we've mentioned throughout the whole
series about how people behave and how
people think. Like a lot of this varies
across generations. So to specifically
talk about each generation hopefully
will be helpful for people to get a
broader idea of what the culture is like
cuz ultimately culture is just made up
of different groups of people. You know
age is such a key category like we've
all experienced different things in our
childhoods. So yeah it should be
interesting. It is funny how you do get
similarities between the generations
that go across countries. So it actually
cuts across national differences,
cultural differences, different
religions, and you talk to different
people and you do find that there are
these similarities. Like as we'll get on
to it, boomers around the world do have
very similar traits, which is very
strange. You you wouldn't think so, but
they do. But let's start with our own
generation, and then we can work back a
little bit, and then we can work
forwards. We're both millennial, aren't
we? We're actually born in the same
month and the same year. So, we're ex in
exactly the same section of our
generation.
>> So, we're currently 32.
>> Yep. We're 32 years of age.
Unfortunately,
>> it's a good age, especially for men.
>> That's true. I am actually really
enjoying my 30s so far, so I shouldn't
complain. Millennials. Yeah. So,
basically, if you're born from the early
80s all the way up to the mid '90s,
you're a millennial. I'd love to know if
our listeners agree with this, too. is
when I think of millennials, I sort of
think of them as a kind of an unlucky
generation.
>> Really?
>> Yes, I do. In some ways, we always get
compared to Gen X and the boomers
because we missed out on a lot of the
the so-called good times in in at least
in the West.
>> Yeah, we missed out on the 80s.
>> We missed out on that.
>> The 80s sounded cool.
>> It did sound very cool. Basically to
explain to our listeners, the boomers
and Gen X, so kind of people born before
us, they kind of lived through very
strong growth years for the West
economically. Economies were growing
fast. There was like more jobs, more
opportunities. If you went to
university, you often didn't have to pay
for it. Almost nobody had a degree, so
it opened lots of doors for you. House
prices were very low. You could get a
big house for not much money. Cars were
cheaper. like there's all kinds of
different advantages that they got
financially that we didn't get. So
that's why when I think of millennials,
I tend to think of them as a bit of an
unlucky generation. We were teenagers
when we had the what's called the great
recession or the credit crunch, which
was the huge financial crisis that
affected the world in 20089. In the UK,
we then had Brexit, which was another
huge moment of chaos for our country.
Lots of uncertainty, bad things
happening. Then we had obviously COVID
which came along in our late 20s. So
we've basically just had it's quite a
joke. It's a joke that people make
online is that we've had three once in a
generation events within the space of 10
years, but you're only supposed to have
one once in a generation thing happen to
you.
>> I just think that one thing's really
lucky for us is that we didn't quite
grow up with social media. I think we
were like what age 14, 15 when Facebook
took off. Our brains were kind of
already formed to a certain extent. I
think that's actually a really good
point. We're probably the last
generation to really have that maybe
more old school way of thinking where
you can just concentrate for long
periods of time and not get distracted
all the time. And I think as well one
thing that we are luckier than previous
generations for is the technology that
we had around us as we grew up.
Smartphones became a thing when we were
in high school. Uh we had the internet
from a very young age. Everything was
digitalizing when we were kids. So we
grew up with all this stuff and we know
how to use it kind of intuitively. Yeah.
Uh we're lucky to have the technology
that we had growing up. So the internet,
computers, smartphones, that's huge. I
got those in high school. Been very
lucky with how things have digitalized
really rapidly from our childhood. But
also we have very very faint memories of
the pre-digital world. I can just
remember a time when most people didn't
have mobile phones and we didn't use the
internet all the time and we weren't on
our phones constantly. So we can just
remember that which I think is quite
important as well.
>> Yeah, 100%. I mean for me that's like
the golden era. I vaguely remember that
as a time before my brain started being
really distracted.
>> Yeah, same. Same. I think things have
changed a lot in the last five, 10
years. Uh especially in terms of uh our
attention spans, which does scare me
quite a lot cuz I just can't concentrate
on things the same as I used to anymore.
>> Like, do you use Tik Tok? You are quite
a big Tik Tok fan, aren't you?
>> I do really like Tik Tok. I've I've
limited myself to 15 minutes a day, but
sometimes I do go over my limit. So, it
is uh
>> Do you actually manage to stick to that?
>> Generally, yes. Instagram I struggle
with more. I should have 15 of that, but
uh generally I can stick to it. So, I
think we're kind of very lucky in some
respects and very unlucky in other
respects. Well, what do you think of
when you think of millennials?
>> I think I've had a few conversations
with my sister about this. So, she's Gen
Z. She's 23. She says we're all about
finding ourselves and trying to escape
and like traveling abroad to just like
be free and we're all about sort of like
self-help and healing and this sort of
thing. like we're sort of quite anxious
and a bit troubled and trying to heal
ourselves. But I wonder if it's also is
it just anyone who's between the ages of
what late 20s and early 40s? Like that's
the most stressful time of life. So
maybe all generations go through that
phase. I don't know.
>> I disagree actually. I think we're a
particularly anxious, over therapized,
very inward-looking, introspective,
possibly self-indulgent generation.
>> Why do you think we're like that?
>> Because I think we were quite spoiled by
our parents' generation, the boomers. I
think they lavished a lot of attention
and made us believe that we were like
super special and that everything had to
be really good for us and that we
shouldn't expect any difficulties in
life. And and then when that's not
matched up with reality, I think this is
all the anxiety, all of the overthinking
and also we've we've grown up in very
uncertain times as well.
>> And what why would the boomers have
spoiled us like that? It's probably
because they grew up in times of more
austerity and they weren't treated so
lavishly. So they're like, "Okay, I'm
going to give my kids what I didn't
have. whatever you want, possibilities,
hopes,
>> especially materially because they did
really well as a generation, they passed
on those high expectations to us, which
again didn't match with reality, hence
all of the anxiety, the disappointment,
the stress.
>> I don't know. Again, I'm not sure if
this is like is is this an experience
that everyone has, but it seemed to me
like there was this bright hopeful
future and then you go to university and
then you go out into the world and
you're like, wait, is this it? Where's
the the bright, you know, exciting
future that I was expecting? Just very
humrum and mundane.
>> I do. Yeah, I know. 100%. I I do think a
lot of people can probably empathize
with that. But yeah, I do I do think we
as as a generation we were sold a little
bit of a dream that just has not come
true in any way, shape, or form.
>> Especially the fact that we a lot of our
generation won't achieve the same
material comfort that our parents did.
Have you seen new studies about classes
and how the class system is changing in
the UK? It was kind of a while ago
actually. I think it was like a 2013
study, but looking at how upper middle
and working class has shifted and a lot
of the middle class are sort of
splitting into like lower middle, upper
middle, a lot of the working class
because of new opportunities, new
technology can move up a bracket in
terms of like income and then the upper
class is like non-existent now like 1 or
2%. But basically that middle class like
a lot of people can't continue that
lifestyle that their parents had. Yes, I
think this is a really key um
development in our generation is the
so-called uh squeezed middle back in the
day sort of our parents' generation. You
could be a single income family. So
maybe just the dad works or something
like that and you'd have enough money
for a decent house. You could have extra
things for your kids, you know,
holidays, toys, bikes, all kinds of
things. And you still have money left
over to save. So you can build up your
wealth quite easily and only one person
in the family is working. You do the
same job for 30 years at the same
company. You retire early, maybe in your
60s, have a really nice pension, and
that's it. You have you have a great
life. That system has basically crumbled
over the past 20 years. No, almost no
one in our generation will retire at 60.
You definitely can't run a family on a
single income. That's almost impossible
now cuz wages have stagnated and costs
have risen. This is the classic
millennial dilemma is how am I going to
buy a house? The ultimate challenge of
our lives is how am I going to buy a
house? Where am I going to buy a house?
I can't get on the property ladder. Blah
blah blah. These are problems that I'm
having right now. And I know you've now
got a property, but it took a while as
well. And you can't get the exact one
you want, and it's tricky. And this is
like a central challenge of our
generation. Materially, we're just not
at the level that we expected. But
that's kind of it. What else did your
sister say about millennials?
>> I think she says that her generation, so
Gen Z, are more kind of practical. Get
on with it. Like a bit more savvy. Yeah.
Millennials are just trying to escape. I
think that's basically the crux of what
she said. I think it's interesting. I
know we're kind of getting into like Gen
Z now, but um yeah, a bit more
levelheaded than we are. They're not I
mean, having said that though, they also
like mental health is a huge part of the
Gen Z.
>> I feel actually really sorry for Gen Z.
I feel like they've had it way worse
than us. They've been the part of the
experiment of social media.
>> That's true. They have been exposed to
that and obviously scrolling stuff and
Tik Tok and all these things. So,
they've been like their brains have been
pulverized by this stuff. But equally, I
do agree with you, they're a bit more
practical, and I think they went into
life with lower expectations than we
did. So, they're not as bamboozled by
how crazy the world is and how difficult
things are. They're just getting on with
it. They're all about side hustles and
doing their own thing. And they're in a
way they're more similar to the boomers
who are much more about get on with it,
find a way, keep working. Whereas, I
think we were sort of caught in the
middle.
>> Yeah. It's like I think we sort of held
on to the tail end of that dream of if I
work hard and I do the right things, I'm
going to be rewarded. whereas Gen Z are
more aware of the fact that no, the
system's not necessarily set up to
reward you. You need to kind of make
your own way. So, they'll put up with
less in terms of work, which I think is
really good and I like that in a way.
Um, but I think that doesn't they don't
really get on with the the older
generations in that sense cuz the older
generations are like, you need to hold
down a job and stick with it and blah
blah blah. And Gen Z is like, it's not
working for me. I'm moving on. And that
I guess that's quite threatening to
older generations who are, you know,
that's been their whole life maybe
sticking with one or two jobs. So to see
someone just dance around and it
actually work out for them is quite
threatening to uh what you've dedicated
your life to.
>> Exactly. It's their whole worldview and
system being ignored essentially by Gen
Z. As you say, if it's not working for
me, I'm not going to do it. They might
say stuff like uh oh yeah, I'm I'm just
not available to work at these times and
just tell their boss that. And their
boss is just like, hang on, but you
haven't cleared it with and they're just
like, "Well, that's what I'm doing, so
get used to it." Which is crazy to even
our generation.
>> I did have a really interesting
experience with a Gen Z teacher who was
due to start with us. And I think there
was, you know, in the beginning
sometimes there's miscommunication.
Everyone sort of learning how things
work. And we didn't have many teachers
at the time, but she basically wasn't
sure if she had a class the next day.
And she sent a really sassy email that
was like, you know, this is totally uh
not okay. And I've been really stressed
not knowing if this class is happening.
I quit and she'd literally just started
like this was like second communication
with her and I was like, "Oh, really
sorry. Um, turns out that class is not
happening or whatever." Sort of I'm
prepared to look past this and obviously
we'll, you know, get a smoother
relationship so you know what's going
on. It turns out that she had made a
mistake or something and I was like,
"Okay, no worries. Are you still going
to be working with us?" She's like, "No,
I still resign." And I was just like
just so baffled like you're resigning
because something didn't quite go the
way that you expected like what are you
going to like all jobs have things like
that right where things are frustrating
it's not always as you expect and it was
just like good luck to you honestly like
if you can't handle that oh my god so I
was reflecting on why did that happen or
how could cuz what I would expect is
someone the first stage is to say hey
not sure if this class is happening just
checking in kind of Like first you ask
the question to try and resolve the
problem. If things are really ongoing
and really frustrating then fair
obviously yeah quit if it's not working
out. But I'm just like how did you skip
the stage where you try to solve the
issue? And for some reason it did make
me think that it might be to do with
generational differences. And I don't
want to like whitewash all of Jen Z and
say that they're all like that cuz
obviously not. I was thinking maybe
maybe she could have had a conversation
with her friends like her flatmates and
they're like, "Wait, you don't know if
this class is happening and you're
stressed? Oh my god, that's so out of
order of them. That's a boundary that
they've crossed." Something like this
where you kind of egg each other on.
It's like, "Yeah, you're right. That's
my boundary. I need to assert." And I
think that's actually quite a a key
difference between Gen Z and
millennials. Millennials are more
apologetic and like, "Oh, it's all me.
It's my fault." And don't really have
strong boundaries, whereas Gen Z are
like, "You've wronged me. I'm going to
assert my boundary.
>> This is a big thing. Yeah, the Gen Z,
they seem to talk about setting
boundaries a lot, whereas we seem to be
recovering from trauma or something like
that. So, yeah, and you're right. We're
super apologetic. That That's exactly
right. We struggle to set boundaries.
Gen Z have no problem setting
boundaries. That is a key difference. I
don't know many Gen Z people to be
honest with you. I think you're better
placed to talk about them than I am. But
the ones that I have known are all very
like, I'm going to do it this way. I'm
going to do it my way. If anything gets
in the way of that then forget it.
>> Yeah. I think it shows up in the way
people talk that is a lot more direct
with Gen Z. I feel like that sort of
soft guess Britishness is kind of
phasing out in a way with the younger
generations.
>> It seems to be actually. Yeah. They we
don't tiptoe around so much anymore
which is a strange thing. So that's uh
the main differences between Jenz and
millennials. I mean, they also make a
lot of fun of us for wearing like ankle
socks and uh skinny jeans, being
obsessed with Harry Potter, using the
wrong emojis, loads of different things.
What else are we obsessed with? Oh,
saying like doggos instead of dog and
like having cutesy words for things and
just generally being extremely cringe.
But obviously that's something that all
generations laugh at older generations
for. But there is currently in the c in
the culture right now, there is this
kind of like Gen Z versus millennial
battle cuz they're replacing us. They're
cooler than us. They're more direct than
us. They've got their heads screwed on a
bit more than we do. And they just find
us very embarrassing.
>> I wonder as well if they've witnessed
our generation and older being really
cringy with the alcohol and taking it
too far and making a fool of ourselves
and they've thought, do you know what? I
don't want to be like that. And so
they've started to drink less.
>> Yes. This is something that really
really surprised me is that Jenzi are
the most abst
are much more abst.
We were basically the last generation to
really overdo it with the booze. We're
one of the booziest generations of all
time. Jenzi are just not interested.
They're much more into it's sort of the
stuff we were talking about on previous
episodes like coffee raves and hikes and
climbing and just doing active stuff.
They don't want to waste their time
getting drunk all the time because for
their generation by the time they came
of age it was too expensive to go out
and do these things whereas we caught
the tail end of it sort of proper night
life whereas Jenzi just aren't
interested in that really which is quite
interesting
>> and it seems like they do make the
decisions more from a place of being
sensible or choosing the life that they
want as opposed to millennials who
sometimes make decisions out of anxiety
or just FOMO or like trying to feel in
control or something. Well, it goes back
to the thing you were saying about
trying to escape. Like we're always
trying to like escape from something or
kind of maybe fantasize a little bit.
And one of the ways that you do that is
by drinking
>> or like or if you were a non-drinker as
a millennial, which I guess I kind of
am. It might be more like I need to
control my health. Yeah.
>> Yeah, I think so.
>> Like really anxious.
>> Whereas for Jenzi, they're just like,
nah, it's expensive. It's a waste of
time. I don't care. I'm not going to do
it. Which is interesting because in the
same way that you were saying like their
directness is very unbritish, not
drinking. I mean that that's a that's a
huge part of our culture that is rapidly
changing with the generations. And I
never thought I'd see the day when
teenagers and people in their 20s were
not going out to the pub and nightclubs
all the time, but they don't anymore.
The notions through the generations, our
notions of Britishness are changing
super super fast. And honestly, I I did
not see any of it coming. And it's
funny, like we're only 32. What's it
going to be like when we're 42, 52? I
mean, it's going to be just completely
and utterly different, you I can't even
imagine what Britain's going to be like
in in that time.
>> Should we get on to Gen Alpha? Again, I
don't know that many people of that age
category, but I know a couple and the
the humor is just a lot more strange.
They seem to like things that are
totally freakish and weird. Like, you
know about Skippy Toilet.
>> I do know about Skippy Toilet. Yeah.
>> Like the fact that that's the thing to
come out of that generation is like,
what is coming next?
>> And then Yeah. And then everything gets
described as Skibbidy, but it it's just
a nonsense word that can mean anything.
Um, I wouldn't recommend to many of our
listeners that you go and watch
Skippidity toilet videos cuz it's what
you call brain rot. It's basically just
stuff that is destroying your brain.
It's it's really like pointless. Having
said that though, Gen Alpha are
associated with this crazy sense of
humor. I don't think it's that different
from our humor because we grew up with
like crazy internet humor.
>> Do you remember Badger Badger Badger?
>> Badger. Exactly. Badger badger.
>> That was already weird, wasn't it? See,
this is why I think I don't think it's
about the actual um the time period or
the people. It's literally just as you
get older, for example, millennials are
more anxious because we've moved into a
higher responsibility phase of life.
That's why our parents would have been
anxious at that time. And then as we get
older again, probably we'll become more
baby boomer, which is we'll talk about
that in a sec, but more kind of get on
with it, dry humor, isn't everything
awful sort of thing.
>> It is interesting that yeah, like you
change as Yeah, obviously we all change
as we get older, but your generation
doesn't stay static. you do ease
yourself into different modes of life
and ways of thinking naturally as you
get older. So, we should explain that
like the generations aren't set exactly
by the time we're old. Yes, some some
aspects of being a millennial will be
the same, but a lot of them will change
as well. It's a very fluid thing. It's
not it's never a set thing.
>> Yeah. I thought it it really highlighted
that fact when I was watching a sort of
an interview about the making of
friends. So, that was obviously in the
'9s and they were talking about, oh, you
know, people saying friends is just like
a Gen X thing. they're just lazy and
they sit around and they do nothing. I
was like, "Oh, that's interesting." So
that was the stereotype about Gen X. So
that's like our parents' generation. I
was slightly younger. Whereas now that's
more Gen Z.
>> Yes. Exactly. Yeah. And and that's also
there's certain things that the
generations always say about the younger
generation that they're not as
dedicated, that they're lazy, that they
don't know what they're doing, that they
their fashion is weird, or maybe their
humor is weird. Like there's actually
records in ancient Greece of generations
complaining about the next generation,
sort of saying like, "Oh, young people
don't read poetry anymore and they don't
want to fight for Athens anymore and
they're lazy and rubbish and and that
was like 3,000 years ago or something."
There's certain generational divides
that have always existed and will always
exist. That's just getting older
basically grumbling about the generation
below you and laughing at the generation
above you. Pretty much that's just what
happens. I think they even more than Gen
X, their whole life is just social
media. Yeah, they're a very like
digitalized generation. It's crazy. Even
for Gen Z, they just live entirely on
their phones and on screens.
>> And I guess they're at the age where
they can and it doesn't really matter.
My sister, who's Gen Z, is becoming more
cautious or conscious of how she uses
social media and stuff, which again just
reflects the fact that she's getting
older and, you know, she wants to be a
bit more serious about achieving
something in her career or whatever.
Yeah, this is also Gen Alpha is also a
generation that they were still very
young when CO hit. A big portion of
their life was spent kind of in
lockdown. They're socialized quite
differently with the younger generations
actually from Gen Z onwards, Gen Alpha,
hopefully not Gen Beta as well, but
apparently just generally speaking, they
socialize in person less. They have
fewer friends than ever before, fewer
romantic relationships. They're not
having as much sex.
>> I witnessed this when I was doing the
masters at Oxford. So, obviously, I was
a mature student. I was over 30. you
know, the other classmates were in their
mid20ies. And over time, I just started
to notice that the cues that I'm used to
where when you're talking to someone,
you look them in the eye and you make
facial expressions that are like, I'm
listening and I'm open to what you're
saying. Didn't seem to be there in quite
the same way. People would do it to each
other. They're sort of not engaging and
then it makes people feel anxious cuz
they're not sure if they're being
listened to. I just definitely noticed
there was something a bit different
about how they engaged with each other.
And I wasn't sure, is this just me? Am I
like now old and I actually have a
different rhythm? Which could also be
the case. You know when you're young and
you're like, "Oh yeah, that old person,
they're fine, but it's kind of hard to
engage with them." Like maybe it was
like that. Or maybe it's sort of co and
lockdowns and social media have affected
the way that people socialize.
>> Yeah. Just the sheer amount of screen
time. You're just not used to
socializing in person. You're not
developing those cues and think that
could very well be a factor in it. But
have you heard about the Gen Z stare?
>> Yeah. Yeah. What say is just like a
blank? They don't kind of emote or
respond in the way that you're going to
they think they're going to. So when
you're talking to them, they're just
kind of like yeah, staring blankly at
you kind of like.
>> That is quite interesting, isn't it? If
it is the case of people just out of
practice.
>> Uh yeah, I hope that consciously our
generation raises them to socialize in
person a lot more. So it will be very
interesting to see if this uh have we
peaked with social use, social media
use, and screen use. And for the next
generation, because we're more aware of
it, they might escape that actually a
less digital generation than the
generation before them, which is quite
interesting.
>> I hope so. Well, Gen beta, so they're
currently newborns born in 2025 onwards.
Gen beta. So, you know, they're not a
thing yet. They're just babies. I have
high hopes. Well, because I'm going to
raise a couple of them, and I'm going to
be like, "No, those screens are have
absolutely no place in our house. I have
no interest." At the moment, I'm feeling
pretty optimistic that I'm going to be
pretty um get out in the real world, use
your body, like socialize with actual
human beings. So, I don't know, you
know, if other parents will be the same,
but I get a sense possibly.
>> I think it'll be very difficult to
reconcile that with uh their school,
which will probably have quite a few
screens involved.
>> They're not going to school.
>> Oh. Oh, of course. Yeah, you're going to
homeschool them. So, you you've you've
covered that one off.
>> Well, we'll see. Yeah, the
practicalities of that might be
different, but yeah, the dream is to
have our own private semihome school
semi on their own, but it's like with
other kids.
>> The Suzie Woo school.
>> Yeah, that's the dream.
>> Dear Lord. Well, um,
>> dear Lord, it's going to be great.
>> I'm just joking. I'm joking. Because our
generation are becoming parents now. It
will be interesting to see if they can
manage that because yeah, the world will
be filled with screens. The world will
be filled with jobs that involve
screens. So AI is another factor. If the
predictions of AI come true, then none
of us are going to be working. So, how
do you prepare your kid for a world
where there's no work?
>> Follow your passion, creativity, think
outside the box. Yeah, I'm quite
hopeful.
>> Certainly with our generation, because
obviously we came off the this huge
disappointment of thinking that it was
going to be like the boomers world and
then it wasn't. I do think we'll empower
our kids generation, Gen beta. I think
we were sort of almost disempowered by
the boomers in a weird way.
>> Yeah. By being molly coddled and looked
after too much. Yeah. And taught that it
was all just going to fall into our laps
basically. But I think with this new
generation, we're over the
disappointment now. So, we're going to
be teaching them, yeah, like get a side
hustle, do this, do that. As you say,
like use your body, be more active. Like
I think they could be a much healthier
generation than our generation that
there's just so many things that will be
involved in their life that we can't
even predict yet. It's kind of exciting,
but it's also kind of worrying. I can
imagine nearly a parent, you must be
thinking about these things quite a lot.
Let's see how gener do. Yeah, I guess
it's more thinking what kind of
experience would I have wanted to have?
And I'm like I think yeah, the school
system doesn't make sense to me. Being
on social media on your own a lot
doesn't make any sense. I'll try and
orchestrate it a bit differently. I'm
probably going to like delude them into
thinking that the future's bright again.
And then they'll be disillusioned just
like we were.
>> See if they do get disillusioned. Maybe
they'll be better than everyone. I
weirdly do have high hopes. I think they
could be really really good. So
basically the millennials have reached
the point where they're having kids and
we have mutual friends who are having
children. Yeah, we're moving to a new
phase of life. So it's uh the
millennials are going to have to get
their act together and be a bit more
grown up because we're parents now. So
yeah,
>> the real privilege now is not being rich
or having opportunities. It's whether
your parents can support you.
>> Wow. It's quite daunting. Yeah.
>> Cuz if you don't have the help of
parents, it's just incredibly difficult
to get by.
>> Yes, that's very true. Yeah, I mean I
can barely support myself as it is. So,
um kind of worried about the amount of
support I'd have to provide for my
children if I do have children, of
course. Why don't we move on now to Gen
X, who are the generation before us.
This is a weird generation in the West
because they kind of go under the radar.
People don't know that much about them
or really care about them that much.
They don't have a big presence in the
culture. Like, people don't talk about
them very much. So they are born between
1965 and 1980 which makes them currently
in their late 40s and 50s.
>> Yes. The very earliest of their
generation is turning 60 now which is
quite crazy. But basically the way I
think of Gen X people is they're
slightly more chilled versions of
boomers who grew up playing video games
and going to raves.
>> Yeah, I think that's quite a good
summary.
>> By raves we mean like big parties in
nightclubs and stuff like that.
>> I feel like they often can be quite
cool, can't they? I feel like they tend
to be more dark. The humor tends to be
more cynical. Maybe
>> they were often in their 20s and 30s
during the '90s. And it's seen as a very
cynical decade after the sort of greed
and excess of the 80s. The '9s is a much
more conscious, cynical, a slightly
darker decade, and that's infused in
their sense of humor and the way they
behave and everything. They're very kind
of anti-corporate, pretty cynical about
the world. But yeah, I think they're
generally quite a chill generation.
They're quite a fun generation. I feel
that millennials can relate to them
quite a lot. They there's a lot of
similarities there, much more than say
millennials to Gen Z. I think there's
less of a gap between millennials and
Gen X. Things like night life, humor,
attitudes to work and stuff like that.
It's pretty similar. But I think we're
more anxious than them. They're more
chilled. I think millennials are more
about trying to solve their trauma that
if their child has a tantrum in the
supermarket, they might come down to the
child's level, be like, "No, this is
about my trauma that's affected you and
now we need to discuss our feelings and
it's very like emotional." Whereas Gen X
would be just get on with it. They're
not going to overshare their emotions.
>> They do share that a slightly more
boomerish aspect where yeah, they are
not so obsessed with their feelings.
They're not so introspective. they're
not so uh anxious. They do blend a
little bit with the boomers. They also
caught the tail end of the boomer's good
years. So, they were still able to get
cheap property. They were still able to
get decent jobs and decent wages. Not
not on the boomers level, but they
caught the very tail end of that I would
say. And I think a few of them did
unfortunately get woped by the 2008
recession. I feel like a lot losing
homes and opportunities, jobs and
things. But yeah, generally pretty chill
generation. Good music, ' 80s, '9s,
2000s. And they also are quite good
because they they have very very clear
memories of the analog world before
digital, but they were still young
enough to click on to the digital stuff
to like learn it really quickly. A lot
of Gen X's can remember when computers
were coming into the workplace and stuff
like that, but they were young enough in
their 20s that they could just learn it
quickly. So they kind of got the best of
both worlds really. That's basically Gen
X. And now unfortunately we must turn
our attention to possibly my least
favorite generation, the baby boomers.
Yes. Our parents' generation. Oh,
they're so annoying.
>> So, just to clarify, they're born
between 1946 and 1964, which makes them
over 60. You find them annoying. Why?
>> Oh, god, they're irritating. Cuz they're
just so like
>> Cuz they're our parents. That's why.
>> Yeah. Exact. Exactly. Yeah. And who
could be more irritating than your
parent? Oh, cuz they just had such an
easy ride and they just act like they
did it all themselves.
>> They're very smug.
>> Yeah. They're so smug. Exactly. Yeah.
They had the easiest ride I think of any
generation. I mean, obviously the world
they grew up in was quite a dangerous
world. You know, there was the Cold War.
There was like a lot of bad stuff
happening. Same with most generations.
But economically, they just had it so
sweet for so many decades. I guess it
depends what job they did though cuz my
parents were GPS and it sounds kind of
awful that they had to work 90 plus hour
weeks. I mean, things have changed. The
working conditions are a bit more humane
now. I Okay, so I will agree with you
that their working life was much more
old school. It was much more hardcore,
shall we say? But their generation had
the advantage of if you were prepared to
put the hours in, you will almost
certainly be rewarded. Not just rewarded
a little bit, you'll be rewarded in
spades because cheap houses, cheap
consumer goods, higher wages to cost
ratio, you could just live a good life
and have a normal job and just have like
a decent life. And they grew up in a
time when the west a lot of western
economies were still growing really
really fast. So loads of opportunities.
>> It's a lot more predictable.
>> Yes. A lot more stable. But you are
right in that their working world is
definitely more hardcore. Effectively
the boomers raised us to expect that our
lives were going to be the same as their
lives which obviously hasn't happened.
It was all about go to university, get a
good job, work really hard, and then
you'll have untold riches and your
life's going to be amazing. That did not
happen.
>> Yeah. It was all about going to
university, wasn't it? I know we touched
on this in our university episode, but
it was like, "Don't bother doing much
else because if you get a good degree,
you're sorted." Which is absolutely
>> Exactly. Yeah. Study, study, study and
be fine. But then they have the the
nerve to sort of have a go at us for
like wasting money and stuff. They sort
of say like, "Oh, well, millennials just
buy avocado toast every morning and if
you save that money, you could buy a
house." And when you add up the money,
it's nowhere near a house. So, it's just
nonsense. So, they still think in terms
of boomer prices of things. That's my
bug bears about the boomers. you know, I
saved up and I got a house and why can't
you do it? And it's just like they don't
understand that things have changed, but
I think a lot of them are pretty kind of
dismissive of us. But then that's what
you do with younger generations, right?
You're supposed to be dismissive of
them. I did my Spotify wrapped recently.
>> Like a compilation of your top songs
over the year, is it?
>> And your listening habits for the year
as well, and my listening age is the age
of a baby boomer. So my listening age is
72. That's the one thing I do envy of
the boomers. just their prosperity, but
I love their music. They have the best
music of any generation. I think my dad
has a poster of all of the old tickets
from gigs he went to, and he just has
like the coolest bands on there, and I'm
always very jealous. I think their youth
culture was unmatched. They had the best
youth culture out of any generation.
Full stop. Does sound great, doesn't it?
Like disco, how fun would that be?
You've got like the sort of set moves.
It's not just like randomly pump your
fist in the air and that's dancing. It's
like everyone can dance together. How
lovely.
>> Exactly. In a cool nightclub setting.
There's also one thing that's very
important to note about the boomers is
that in Britain and in the West, they
were the generation that basically um in
a lot of cases lost their religion. So
this is a huge generational gap from our
grandparents generation, the boomers
often became atheist.
>> Oh, and of course it was the
introduction of the contraceptive pill
in their generation.
>> Exactly. Which is another huge huge
difference. So basically our
grandparents generation when you dated
someone you dated to marry you didn't
date for very long and you normally got
married at like 20 had some kids
finished the boomers were able to take
their time a bit in the 60s there was
the beginnings of yeah what you'd call
free love and liberalization where you
weren't expected to marry straight away
and have kids straight away. You could
have multiple partners. You could
experiment. You could find your own way.
That was tied to a loss of religion as
well. Obviously, Christianity says you
must uh marry before you can have sex.
You must have sex to have children, etc.
The boomers did quietly kind of put all
that in the bin pretty much. And that's
what we inherited. So, our ways of
romantic life and social life are
basically inherited from the baby
boomers, not from our grandparents
generation. So, that's a huge
generational divide between our
grandparents and parents. Probably among
the biggest out of all of them, to be
honest with you. What's great is they
had this liberalization without totally
changing the economic system yet.
Whereas now, if you don't have two
working parents, you can't basically
make it. You could still have just the
dad working. Whereas now, you know what
I mean?
>> Let's round things off with the last uh
generation we're going to touch on,
which is the silent generation.
>> I have to say I don't really know
anything about this generation. I wasn't
that close with my grandparents.
>> Ah, I see. That's interesting. I still
am close with my remaining grandparent.
So this generation was born basically
before the second world war. That's the
thing to note about them. They were born
in the 1920s and 30s and I think the
mid-40s. Big difference between their
generation and all of the subsequent
generations is that a lot of them grew
up with very little material wealth. In
some cases would not really have a lot
of food in the house, not being able to
heat the house to afford fuel, lived in
very small, cramped houses with big
families. That's a that's a huge
difference between the silent generation
and the boomers is that the silent
generation in the west still grew up
with massive families which is not a big
feature of the west anymore. It would be
very normal to have like five 6 7 8 nine
siblings and all live in a house
together very cramped conditions not a
lot of money. It was um a very difficult
life basically and fortunately when they
came of age after World War II that's
when things started to get better. So
their generation saw a huge change in
their wealth and their material
circumstances. Basically, that's the
defining characteristic of that
generation. When they were growing up,
they had very little. By the time they
got old, they had loads. Well, in a lot
of cases, not in every case, of course,
but that is a big big trend of their
generation.
>> No, this generation is coming back to me
now through stories from my dad about
his childhood. And uh so he had four
siblings. Sounds like they basically
just weren't really given enough to eat.
He would be sent to bed at 6:00 p.m.
when the sun was out. I think they
weren't very nice in other ways. Yeah.
the sort of level of deprivation that
you're describing.
>> I think this actually informs a lot of
the boomers attitudes to us because
often times their parents were quite
negligent. Sort of raise yourself
almost. They'd be very strict and
disciplinarian, but by and large they
didn't want to hear from you. They
didn't do a lot of parenting. They just
kind of let you do what you wanted.
>> My dad said he was basically raised by
his older sister who was like 20 years
older than him.
>> Yeah. They're very, very common. As long
as you provided for your children, that
was it. You weren't expected to do much
more than that. It's like
>> keep them alive.
>> Exactly. Keep them alive. I mean, I
remember my dad saying his dad, my
grandfather, I don't think ever took him
to the cinema, for example, like once in
their whole childhood. Basically, he
earned the money and that he saw that as
his duty and that was it. Basically,
there's not like, oh, how are you
feeling today? Oh, uh, how's this going?
How's that going? Helicopter parenting,
which is what the boomers did to us,
where they're like so obsessed with your
progress and your how you're doing as a
a person because they didn't get that
from their parents. Wasn't it child
centric parenting only came in from the
80s or something like that? That's this
whole shift towards, you know, what does
the child need?
>> Basically, yeah. The second half of the
20th century is when people began to
realize, oh, you can actually like do a
bit more for your kids than just feed
them. It became fashionable to kind of
care about more than that in their life,
basically. Yeah. They're a very quite a
strange generation that there's just a
big big divide between them and us and
them and the boomers. They're kind of on
their own really because they're often
more religious, much more socially
conservative. These big families that
they grew up with. Again, the material
conditions of their childhood were
completely different to ours. They lived
through the Second World War, which is
crazy to begin with. Yeah. They're just
of very, very different, very different
values, different ways of seeing the
world.
>> And the class system was really, really
strong at that point. This is where we
get the stereotypes about, you know, the
posh and the working class.
>> You were much more expected to stay in
your class. and the idea of social
mobility, being able to move between
classes, that only really picked up
speed, say from about the 50s onwards.
Before that, forget it. Basically, also
the divide between men and women was
much much more extreme. So my when my
grandma went to school, for example, she
was just taught to cook and clean. She
was actually actively discouraged from
learning maths or English because they
thought, well, you're going to be a wife
anyway, so it doesn't matter. You don't
need to learn these things. So, she was
genuinely discouraged from getting an
education at school, which is insane.
>> Which again makes sense that because the
contraception hadn't even been invented
then. So, it's like, well, you probably
are just going to have children and
that's it.
>> Yeah. Get to about 20, get married, pop
a few kids out, and that's your life.
Get used to it. Another thing would be
the expectation that you might not even
live that long. In your 60s and 70s, you
probably will die of something because
medicine wasn't as good. Yeah. Very,
very different views of life. So, it's
kind of hard to relate to them. Do you
know what sort of lifestyle or position
your grandparents were in? Cuz I think
mine were quite interesting. I feel like
on my mom's side, her parents were more
workingass whereas my dad's were more
like middle upper class, but at the same
time they sort of struggled. So they
were academics but they weren't earning
huge amounts of money. So it's things
like academia, music, all of that very
very important, but at the same time
struggling to feed their family, which a
bit of a strange combination. Generally
not having a lot of money around is a
defining characteristic of the
generation. But your dad's side would be
the exception, not the rule because the
middle class was much much smaller back
then. Basically the vast majority of
people in their generation were working
class which meant you do a job to do
with your hands like a physical job.
Farmer, coal miner, ship builder,
whatever. My grandparents, their story
is much more typical of their
generation. Very difficult upbringing.
Get through World War II then things
start to improve. And actually on both
sides of my family they made the
transition from being workingass to kind
of lower middle and middle class. It's a
very very typical story. So did a
working job before the war kind of in
the middle of the war things improve and
then they end up in a managerial
position or set up their own business or
they get a white collar job they were
able to transition and that's um very
good because their lives improved
hugely. A story we always told in the
family that at my grandma's school this
is my dad's mom there were kids at
school who didn't have shoes. you know,
they were just running around barefoot.
They didn't they couldn't even afford
to. And this is in the north of England
in the 1920s. I mean, it's freezing
cold. You can't heat your house half the
time. You got little barefoot kids
running around. I mean, it's a it's a
completely different universe. I mean,
they grew up in the era of like horses
and buggies basically instead of cars.
It's just a different universe. So, it's
very hard to relate to them basically is
the is the bottom line.
>> And also, I feel very sorry for anyone,
you know, over the age of what, 80,
having to deal with all this technology
now. like you can't do anything without
a login and a passcode and a whatever
facial recognition. Really frustrating.
>> This is very typical of their generation
is yeah frustration with technology
because they were just too old by the
time the world was digitalizing. I mean
that some of them had already retired
when the internet came along when mobile
phones came along. They don't have a
clue basically.
>> I think it's actually really lovely that
that's still around that culture that
still exists. like people are still
using mail and actually going to their
neighbor's house to ask them something
rather than sending a WhatsApp message.
I think that's so lovely that still
exists.
>> Looking up something in a book instead
of googling it. You actually had to like
use your brain and find the part of the
book that would tell you like an
encyclopedia or something. You had to
like actually have books in the house
and read and think. And I do agree in
some ways their lives were actually
better. We should just briefly touch on
the generation above, the silent
generation who are called the greatest
generation. They are the generation that
fought in World War II. Well, this
generation is now in their 90s really in
and to be honest in the back end of the
'90s. So, they're rapidly like vanishing
from before us. Um, so really in the
next 5 to 10 years, there'll be nobody
left who fought in the Second World War
who really remembers the Second World
War except as a child. It's a bit of a
worry because I think when these things
start passing into history, it means
that you can start making the same
mistakes all over again. It is quite sad
um to see them to see them pass away.
Obviously, it's it's sad when anyone
passes away, but yeah, it it's it's a
particular generation that lived through
the biggest conflict in human history
and fought in it. So, to kind of see
them leave, it does make me a bit
apprehensive about the future sometimes.
The only people I can remember from this
generation were like older people that I
knew as a child. So, sort of like great
aunties. And I don't know anyone from
this generation now, unfortunately.
>> Me neither. But I guess it's a good
place to end. We have a lot to owe them
to be fair. If we think about how the
trajectory of the 20th century has gone,
yeah, would not be quite the same if it
was not for those people. So, if there
does happen to be anyone over the age of
98 listening, we we are grateful to you.
>> Yes. Thank you very much. Thank you.
Somehow something tells me that perhaps
we haven't cornered that demographic
just yet. But anyway,
>> you never know.
>> You never know. You never ever know. But
yeah, that's uh that's everything for
this episode and for this series. Um
we're finishing here. You know, let us
know how we're doing. Keep uh sending in
questions and we'll be back hopefully
with another series for you. Loads more
topics about Britishness and life in the
UK. Um it's been a lot of fun. How have
you found it, Suz?
>> Are we calling it a series or a season?
>> I think we should call it a series cuz
that's the British way of saying it.
Fair. Okay.
>> Did I say season?
>> Yeah, series sounds good. Um, it's been
great. I'm actually impressed that we
managed to get to episode 10. There was
a point where we uh we both sort of
forgot or didn't turn up for various
reasons. Yeah, I'm I'm pretty impressed
that we've actually managed to come this
far. Now, it's a case of just getting it
out there and hopefully someone listens.
>> And yay,
>> if you are listening, send us more
questions because there's so much more
that we can talk about and we can make a
new series, which we would love to do.
But until then, yeah, um, keep
listening, keep learning, and we'll see
you, uh, we'll hopefully see you very
soon.
>> See you soon. Bye, guys.
>> Bye.
Heat. Heat.